this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers are you ready it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently when you can
make faster decisions there's no telling
what you'll create ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems comm
slash try to try iris hello this is
conscience shrinky for software
engineering radio my guest today is Joe
Kutner
Joe is a software architect at
salesforce.com working on the Hiroko
platform he's a founding member of the
cloud native bill packs project this
project is based on hero who technology
that helped make 12 factor methods
popular Joe has written three books for
the pragmatic bookshelf including
deploying the JRuby and the healthy
programmer Joe has spoken at several
conferences on the 12 factor app welcome
to software engineering radio Joe
hi I'm glad to be here today we will be
talking about the 12 factor app what it
is and how it can help developers and
teams building modern applications I
would like to start with asking you Joe
what is the app in the 12 factor app
well the 12 factor app is a methodology
or a manifesto and it was written or
published by Heroku back in I think 2012
so it's getting getting pretty old now
eight or nine years old and it described
a way of building and deploying
applications that was better suited to
the emerging cloud technologies at the
time
because you have to remember before 2012
most of us were deploying our
applications on in-house data centers
and very few folks were even using AWS
at the time so the the tools and
technologies that we use to build our
apps and to put them into production was
more reminiscent of the early 2000s and
so when Heroku came along they
a new paradigm for deployment that's the
platform as a service and with that came
a new more modern way of
defining your application preparing it
for production and ultimately for
deployment
I see so did the experience at Heroku
supporting the apps get better after the
methodology was published and could you
also maybe give us a couple of examples
of what triggered writing the factors
yes so at Heroku today we host I think
more than 10 million applications we
handle about 23 billion requests per day
so we're seeing a lot of different apps
on a platform and we have you know just
our company essentially operating them
so one of the like real tenants of
Heroku when it was first created was to
be opinionated about how you should use
the platform and how you should create
your apps to run on the platform so the
12 factor app was really a part of that
set of opinions that we had to encourage
our users our customers to build their
apps in a certain way that that worked
better on the platform not only for us
to operate them but also for our
customers to ultimately scale better to
have better security and and better
maintainability characteristics so did
that start happening after this was
published yeah it did I mean in fact the
some of the ecosystems that we supported
at Heroku originally was exclusively the
Ruby language and the Ruby on Rails
ecosystem we're very quick to adopt
these principles they were just well
suited to those technologies but over
time several years we've now seen that
pretty much every ecosystem whether it's
Java or Python or nodejs
are really embracing these principles
and
part of that is because of the
initiative that Heroku took to push
these ideas but it's also about just the
fact that it it led to these better
correct characteristics and the end
result is yeah when you deploy an app on
a platform like Heroku and there are
other other platforms that are just as
suitable for 12 factor apps it ends up
being a better experience for both the
customer the user of the platform and
the folks operating it
as you mentioned it's been some time
since these were published so how
applicable are these now with all the
advances we've seen with microservices
they're wops and containerization I
think there's a lot of things that have
changed but I think the most remarkable
thing is how much it's still the same
how much these principles really still
apply I think many of them you know at
Heroku we've definitely revisited and
and sort of reconsidered but at the end
of the day these are still the design
principles that we use for the majority
of our applications I think there's a
few areas especially when it comes to
micro services where we've loosened up
our opinion on for example the the first
factor which is code and using source
code version control systems and that
you should only have one application per
code repository I still feel that way
but we definitely internally use mono
repos that are that include many
different micro services so there are
times where I think you need to know
when to step away from the paradigm and
do something a little bit different but
for the most part it holds up even in a
world where we're deploying to
kubernetes with docker again very
different from the cloud ecosystem when
Heroku was first created and when the 12
factor app was first published so would
you add more principles at this time
yeah I think so but 12 is such a good
number I think there are definitely some
principles that if we were written today
I think would be included one of those
is security and I should say this is the
idea of adding more principles really
came from a book called beyond the
twelfth factor app written by Kevin
Hoffmann and one of the yes one of those
principles is security the idea that the
security of our applications should come
first it shouldn't be an afterthought we
shouldn't tack security on to the the
end of an application this
you know I think not something we
considered in the same way ten or
fifteen years ago when HTTP was not
everywhere you know now it's very easy
to get a certificate for your
application with let's encrypt but also
things like using role based access to
your resources so that you can have a
good audit trail these are things that
need to be built into your applications
design upfront
another principle that I think is really
worth including in the 12 factor app is
telemetry and so in the book beyond the
12 factor app Kevin makes this analogy
to a space probe like your application
is like this craft that you're sending
into space and it's not coming back to
Earth so if there's a problem with it
when it's in orbit you can only rely on
the instrumentation that you installed
before it was launched and so we need to
think about our apps that run in the
cloud the same way if there's a problem
in production you need to have the
metrics the telemetry the tools that you
need to debug that right there with it
designed you know included with it
upfront so we'll put a reference to the
book beyond the 12 factors in the show
notes so that readers can reference that
too so my neck question would be is
building a 12 factor app easier with
specific programming languages or
platforms or architectural styles yeah
it's definitely lends well to certain
language ecosystems but again it's you
know eight or nine years later most
ecosystems have have picked up these
principles in the Java ecosystem I think
the vast majority of Java developers are
working with spring boot which is very
intentionally designed to embrace the 12
factor principles so everything that's
on the happy path for a spring boot
application is just 12 factor right and
so it makes it very easy there are other
ecosystems that I think like PHP have
not kind of come around fully to these
ideas and you have to you have to
embrace technologies that might not be
as mainstream as as others but for the
most part I think it's permeated just
about every major popular programming
language and programming language
ecosystem that makes sense I personally
checked and I saw that all the major
cloud vendors actually reference these
principles so we'll have some of those
references in our show notes as well
could you talk about single page apps or
mobile apps or service list apps do all
the principles apply for these are
potentially a subset yeah it depends I
think for things like serverless I'm a
little biased but I think serverless is
not that different from what we have had
on like on a modern paths for a really
long time it's just sort of a new way of
thinking about how you write the code
so yeah the certainly the the idea of
disposability which is one of the twelve
factor principles is that's really what
serverless is all about is that I can
dispose of this function or this you
know this this unit of work at a whim
you know I can scale to zero or whatever
it may be and then of course how you
manage your backing resources and and
your configuration I think that's all
still very much the same when it comes
to single page apps it's definitely a
little different I mean you don't have
exactly the same concerns about
scalability on the back end the idea of
processes or disposability might be very
different but certainly how you manage
your code how you manage your
configuration I think all of those
things still apply so you mentioned a
few things configuration disposability
and these are all principles that are
outlined in the twelve factor app could
you maybe just give us the broad areas
before you know we in the later in the
show we will drill our drill into some
of these principles but could you just
give us a broad area of what all these
cover yeah I think that's actually very
doable because so many of them are
interrelated I thing
there's two parts of the factors one is
about how you manage your configuration
and your deployment
you know such that you aren't
hard-coding secrets and such that you
don't have these like snowflake builds
that ship to production and then there's
another set of principles that are more
related to like the operational side of
running in production and those are like
disposability and stateless processes
where it's really intended to favor an
application that is scaleable that can
run in the cloud and that you'll be able
to maintain for a very long time so I
think those are the that's really the
foundation of the 12 factor apps
scalability maintainability okay let's
shift gears a little bit now and let's
talk about the team with adopting these
principles change the development
process or the team composition I'm not
sure about the team composition
definitely there are elements of this
that affect how you work on your
applications one of the principles is
dev prod parity and this is a principle
that encourages you to make your
development environment as similar to
your production environment and your
staging environment all the other
environments as similar as possible and
so for for a lot of developers this is
different from how we typically do local
development you have an instrumented
process that can hot load code which is
still fine but in the 12 factor way of
doing things you're going to run it a
little bit more like you would run it in
production and so that can be a big
shift for people and I think it's one of
the the principles that we again have
kind of backed off a little bit on
because those those local development
tools that sort of break 12 factor they
really increase people's productivity so
I think it's important to be able to run
an application locally with with dev
broad parity but again you need to know
when to eject and use the tools that
just help you get your job done can the
principles the category
into mandatory versus very important was
as nice to have the reason I ask is can
a team pick a few of these principles to
start let's say if they're refactoring
an app or is it necessary to implement
all of them to see the benefits I think
it really depends on your deployment
target on what the platform that you're
gonna run on production supports right
so on a platform like Heroku which is
very opinionated you don't have a great
deal of choice like this is the way
Heroku works and if you want to do
logging a different way it might just
not work now other platforms give you a
little bit more flexibility I think when
you consider something like logging or I
think logging is probably the best
example maybe admin tasks a platform
might handle these in a different way
and then you can choose whether you want
to log to standard out as you're sort of
like an event stream or if you want to
log two files and have something rotate
them you could also choose to rather
than running admin tasks in their own
container you know creating a shell into
a container and running them there so if
the platform gives you the ability to do
those things yes you have a choice but I
think most platforms that are similar to
Heroku comes to mind is like Cloud
Foundry and and Google's App Engine
they're essentially requiring the same
kinds of things the same principles so
it sounds like the team would need to
decide based on the platform and maybe
prioritize based on what the platform
occurs but implementing even a few is
beneficial it's a fair yeah I think
that's fair okay we'd like to now drill
into some of the factors it may not be
possible to cover all of them so let's
start with the ones that I have found
hard to understand or seem more
important so let's start with the
declaration and isolation of
dependencies could you describe this one
right this principles
dates that your dependencies the
dependencies of your application should
be explicitly declared and managed and
so I think the best way to understand
this principle is to look at the inverse
which is where you have dependencies
that are expected to be on the host or
you're not defining as part of your
application you're defining them
somewhere outside of your application so
for example the runtime that executes
syou're code whether it's a JVM or a
node.js runtime if you don't have an
explicit version you're not managing how
that is installed it becomes just this
like global dependency that's that's not
well managed in the Java ecosystem we
also see people that are you know
checking compiled binary jar files into
their source code repository rather than
using the proper dependency management
systems like maven or Gradle to include
those in a way that's both a better
development experience locally but also
easier to manage as part of your CI CD
process would you examples of dependency
management for some other languages
other than Java yeah I think if you're
using NPM and you're using your package
JSON for a node.js application as long
as you are including all of the things
that your application needs to run in
production as part of that dependency
management solution and NPM then you're
abiding by this principle and it's also
okay to combine technologies we see a
lot of applications that have a ruby gem
file and a package.json or they're they
have a pom.xml for Java and a
package.json because they have some fun
end assets that need compiling or you
know preparing for production so every
ecosystem has some dependency management
solution for this and it's really about
using that the way it's supposed to be
used rather than depending on you know
the implicit presence of some execution
engine that you're going to call out to
or something like that
what can have
if the development team does not pay
attention to this principle well
certainly you can run into cases where
you expected one version of a dependency
to be present and it was not there was
some other version and then you get you
know an interface and compatibility at
runtime you know I guess in the worst
case scenario that dependency you
expected to be there is not there and
things things break pretty quickly but I
think it it also leads to problems with
security in terms of being able to audit
what is actually running in your
production environment and sometimes in
your again your CI CD process how do you
manage that the deployment target has
all of the things that you need in order
to get the application working so how
does a team validate our be sure that
they have actually followed this
principle yeah there are I don't know if
there's a really good way I think this
is one of those problems that many
people have tried to solve by you know
instrumenting the environment to see if
you're calling outside of the
application but I think it's I think
it's a real challenge to to correctly
verify this and that's why we see a lot
of security folks working on mechanisms
for image scanning to see if they can
just catalog everything that's in the
image it's a difficult thing to know if
you have some dependency that you
haven't really captured well so I'm not
sure if there is a good way so you
mentioned image can you define that a
little bit further yeah when I say image
I mean essentially a docker image or in
more generically an OCI image but this
the same principles are true for any
kind of image format which could be a
virtual machine image or even as simple
as a tarball
in some cases
but the process that I was referring to
was some tool that can scan the image
and inspect what is inside of it and
catalog that so you can audit it let's
talk about the configuration principle
which says store configuration in the
environment why do that right so the
main purpose of this principle is to
encourage you to decouple configuration
from the application so I think the
principle states specifically that you
should not check your secrets your
passwords into your version control
system and I know most people would not
check their own personal password or at
least I hope they wouldn't into their
git repository but many of us have
checked in an AWS token or a database
password and doing this creates two
problems one the source code repository
is not encrypted so when you store it
somewhere even if it's on a private
server it's still stored in clear-text
so it's a security problem
[Music]
but it's also a problem for portability
because when you start to couple your
configuration whether it's credentials
or you know some other aspect of how the
application executes when you couple
that to the application it then becomes
difficult to move that application to a
different environment without actually
changing the code so in in the worst
cases you know changing your database
requires making a commit and then
deploying that commit which greatly
complicates the process if you have for
example a security problem with your
database and you need to remediate it by
rolling the credentials well now you
have to deploy your application rather
than just changing your configuration
and that can be very problematic
are any recommendations about handling
sensitive information like certificates
or API keys are they handled differently
than other configurations yes it depends
on the type of configuration I think in
the 12 factor app it's explicitly states
that these things whatever they are
should be stored as environment
variables and this is the way Heroku
works even for certificates and things
like that will often store them as a
text string and an environment variable
and then some other process will take
that and write it to disk or you know do
whatever needs to be done we see this
with like java key stores that just
they're not really they're an old
specification and not really designed to
work well with environment variables but
as time has gone on and we have new
technologies like kubernetes and docker
the need to put these secrets or to
store them as environment variables has
kind of changed and we're starting to
see new mechanisms where file mounts can
be used to sort of inject secrets as
files into the container and so this
opens up a lot of other opportunities a
lot of other possibilities for how you
store your secrets how you store your
configuration how you consume them one
of the advantages that storing them as
files has is that it makes it possible
to reload them without restarting your
application and this was always kind of
a problem with environment variables is
you start a process your application
process in an environment and it has a
database URL or an AWS token environment
variable and then it has it and that's
it and there's no way to swap that out
without just restarting the process but
by storing Emma's files gives us you
know the opportunity to hot reload a new
database connection or something like
that is this one easier to test for that
you have actually followed it yes I
think so the litmus test for this
principle is if you can open source your
code at any moment and not compromise
the credentials to your systems then you
are likely satisfying this principle
now determining that is non you know not
necessarily simple but there's some
great tools that you can use with like
get as a pre-commit hook and it'll scan
your code to check for things as simple
as like password equals and then to see
if there's an actual value there so
there's some tools that you know a lot
of IT teams will recommend you have
installed on your on your local
development machine to make sure that
even by accident don't you know don't
get those secrets into your version
control system okay let's move on to the
next one which is treating backing
services as attach resources I wasn't
gonna pick this but you mentioned
backing services earlier so I'd like to
drill into that can you give us some
examples of water backing services
yeah backing services are any service
that you need your app to consume as
part of its operation so this could be a
database it could be a caching service
it could be an APM that's you know
instrumenting your application and
collecting metrics it could be a service
that you use to send emails it could be
a service that you use to collect social
media data these are all examples of
backing services and they're all
essentially external to your app they're
external resources that are likely out
of your control or in some cases you're
choosing to be out of your control like
a database because you want to decouple
the application from it and for each of
these systems for each of these backing
resources we want to treat them like
they are just that sort of these
attachable and detachable components
that we can plug and unplug and what
this allows us to do is swap them in and
out if we need to for example if you are
having a database that is unhealthy and
it needs to be backed up and replaced
with a follower database that mirrors
the data you can do this by creating the
the follower database setting up the new
environment variable or or secret on the
file system with the
the database URL and then having the app
preload that or restarting the
application but you don't have to then
commit to your code or or do anything
else like that
you're just swapping out this like
pointer to the service so this backing
service could be something external or
something that was developed by the team
or related teams so is it fair to say
that backing service itself could be a
twelve factor app oh absolutely and I
think a lot of micro service
architectures treat their services this
way they might even be developed by have
the same person right but there's a need
to decouple them for whatever reason
maybe they're doing different jobs maybe
they have different scalability
requirements and you want them as
separate things but you still want that
ability to replace them with a different
implementation or to have a failover
instance or something like that
calling all developers there's no
telling what you can create when you
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris are you ready to build the
applications you want however you want
them are you ready to develop
applications faster than ever
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today inner systems iris
data platform ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems.com
slash try to try iris okay next one
we'll pick a stateless processes it
states that you should execute the app
as one or more stateless processes what
does that mean this means that there
shouldn't be anything held in memory by
the application that needs to exist
beyond the life of that process so the
best example is sticky sessions or
sometimes called session affinity where
a user who is browsing a website and has
a session that's stored on the server
side that it needs to be stored in the
memory of a single process and this is
really a matter of scalability again
because if a single user needs to return
to that process in order to get their
session it means that you're going to
have
distributing your users across the many
processes that you have it also means
that you can't have a disposable process
right so if that's process contains a
user's session and a user may be using
your website or shopping cart or
e-commerce website for half an hour then
that process if it shut down will
degrade their experience so the
stateless processes reads as execute the
app as one or more stateless processes
why multiple why more what is what is
the significance of having the
application be more than one process
well this is really about scalability if
your application is a single process you
might not mind having some memory ins or
some session or some other data in the
memory of that process but as soon as
you scale out to two processes you now
have to figure out a way to share that
memory between the two processes because
otherwise it's local to that container
or to that machine so the reason that we
want stateless processes is to sort of
decouple the parts of our applications
memory that need to live beyond the life
of that process so that we can use it
from other processes so you can imagine
a user on a website has a session and
when they come back to the website a
couple minutes later they might their
request might be handled by a separate
process but that ID that represents
their session can still be used to go
retrieve their session data from some
external thing that's holding on to that
state in that memory and usually that
thing is a backing service a memcache
tour a Redis moving on to port binding
it says export services wire port
binding could you clarify yeah I think
this one is confusing because you have
to understand what we were doing with
our applications before this principle
came around so the best example is in
the Java ecosystem where as far back is
like the 1990s we had
these application servers that we would
start up and they would bind to a port
and they would do the work of handling a
request but the actual business logic
was contained in a unit of distribution
called the war file that we would drop
into that running application server and
then the application server would kind
of curry the requests into that web
application that was contained in the
war file and it would do something and
then the idea was that we could swap out
that war file with a new one reload it
hot deploy it but that never worked
because of memory issues and crashes and
whatever else so what the 12 factor app
is saying is let's not do that model
let's have our applications be
completely self-contained your
application should know how to connect
to a port handle a request and then also
pass it on to your business specific
logic now you might have a library
that's doing that for you but you don't
have some external resource that knows
how to do that
so this kind of comes back to the
dependency factor where we talked about
not having these external dependencies
that are unmanaged those application
servers of old were essentially an
unmanaged dependency so what we're
describing in port binding or what we're
encouraging is to take that server to
embed it into your application to make
it a dependency of your application this
ultimately makes your application more
portable so you don't need to have that
application server running locally or on
another environment that you're going to
stand up for testing or staging because
your application is self-contained you
just run that jar file or that
JavaScript file or whatever it is and it
has everything it needs to bind to the
port handle requests and do the business
logic so you had mentioned the book
beyond the 12 factor app in that Kevin
Hoffman says that this one may be a
little difficult to build depending on
the infrastructure or the type of
application he says what's most
important is that there should be a
one-to-one correlation
in between the application and the
application server would you agree with
this simplification I think I probably
would not if I think I know what he's
talking about he's I think he's giving
some room to use those application
servers and again this is this comes out
of the Java ecosystem primarily and that
model worked well for people and they
they didn't want to change it but in a
in a world of containers and kubernetes
and cloud native applications I think
the the self-contained processes is
really what's what's important so he
does mention the one-to-one mapping I
think that's characteristic of these
application servers it was very common
in the application server world to have
one port and then a whole bunch of
applications behind that and there's
some kind of router that was like saying
this kind of request that maybe this
path or whatever it may be would be
routed to this application so again that
that starts to you know muddy the waters
of portability and and deaf broad parity
where it's difficult to reproduce that
environment in other places the next
factor is concurrency which says kala
why are the process model that sounds
quite related to what we talked earlier
about processes is it just building upon
that yeah I think it is related
especially in a pre cloud native world
where we were managing our own servers
where resources were limited you know in
order to scale up you needed to buy a
new server we had a tendency to scale by
making bigger and bigger processes with
larger thread pools and more memory and
many of the technologies that we use
like the JVM are very good at this
but we also need to consider that some
types of applications need to be able to
scale out more processes more instances
of your application rather than bigger
processes but also in creating different
types of processes that do different
jobs
so you might have a pool of processes
that are doing some kind of background
work like worker processes and then a
pool of processes that are handling just
web requests this allows you to scale
them independently you may need hundreds
or even thousands of instances to handle
your your web requests but if you have a
nightly job you only need one or two
processes to do that and when we were
building these kind of monolithic
applications where we're relying on
bigger processes with lots of thread
pools it becomes difficult to separate
those different jobs and scale them
independently so that's what this
principle is encouraging is to split
those jobs up run them as processes
again in the cloud the containers the
processes are relatively cheap compared
to that old way of doing things
def brought parity I think I've heard in
couple of your talks you mentioned that
you believe this is the most important
is that still true yes it's true I think
this is one of the most important
principles unfortunately it's also a lie
and it's it's not possible
I think anymore maybe defraud parity is
the right spirit but I think it's
inevitable that there are going to be
differences and you're especially in
your local development environment you
know the spirit of this principle is
still true you should strive to be
capable of running your application
locally the exact same way that you run
it in prod and staging this is important
because it allows your app to be more
portable which allows you to like
reproduce new environments so you can
stand up new environments you can get
new developers started very quickly
because if you can stand up a new
staging environment very quickly why not
get a new developer ramped up and all of
that leads to another one of the factors
which is disposability because if you
can stand these up very quickly well you
can dispose of them and when you don't
need them anymore so that's why I feel
that it's this sort of lynchpin for the
whole methodology but at the same time
you know I really like it when my local
development process hot loads my code
changes and I don't have to do anything
clever to restart it or wait for that
whole restart cycle to load my code
changes I there's nothing wrong with
that but I do think the ability to have
broad parity maybe even if you're not
using it every step of the way in your
development process it's still important
maybe one of the things that makes this
difficult to do is data at least that's
definitely been my experience o the
databases and the backing services
essentially right
not just the backing service but the
actual data is that important oh yeah I
see what you mean
oh yeah
it's it's hard to you know especially
reproduce certain cases without the
right kind of data I never recommend
connecting to your production database
from your local development environment
I want to make that very clear but a
common pattern that I do use is to have
a sort of remote staging environment or
rather a remote development environment
that's very similar to my staging
environment and so very often when I'm
doing development I don't even have my
database running locally I'm actually
connected to a cloud database and in
that case it's sometimes easier to have
either a very large data set that is
reminiscent of the production data or
just to have systems that are handling
kind of like real world transactions and
whatever it may be to get data that is
you know more typical of what will
actually be there and in production as
far as this principle the recommendation
was the developer should write code and
ideally it should be deployed you know
hours or minutes later and if you don't
pay attention to that that's a problem
if the gap is long and also it also
talks about in terms of who deployed the
code was it a completely different
DevOps engineer or the developer himself
can you talk more about that yeah I
think when there is a lack of dev prod
parity there is a tendency to deploy
less frequently or even to decouple the
deployment process from the person who
developed the code and what that results
in is a very long iteration a very long
cycle between writing the code and then
actually verifying that it's working in
production and so part of what dev prod
parity strives to do is tighten that
cycle tighten that loop so that as a
developer after you write code when you
run it locally because of debt
prosperity you have a high level of
confidence that what you're running is
exactly or very similarly the same as
what's running and
and that allows you to verify that your
code is working validate that you don't
have any bugs or very few bugs and
ultimately allow you to be more
productive allow you to have a high
level of confidence that the code you're
writing will work in production so
there's no mention of automation in the
twelfth factors but to reduce these gaps
automation of the deployment seems very
very critical is that right
yeah I think a lot of even though it's
never called out explicitly I think a
lot of the 12 factor principles really
lend to continuous deployment continuous
integration where these processes are
just happening right you push your code
to github it's automatically picked up
and compiled or packaged created and you
know built into an image that's then
executed on some container environment
again just kind of closing the loop very
quickly on your development cycle I you
know I don't remember I kind of wonder
if when the 12 factor app was written if
the CI CD you know moniker or buzzword
was was used at the time but I suspect
it just wasn't something that was talked
about in the way that we talk about it
now and similar to many other
technologies that have come around like
like docker that are inspired by these
principles so they I think they've even
when the 12 factor app doesn't
explicitly call out a connection to
docker or containers or CI CD it's the
spirit of these principles that led to
the way that we do the things we do
let's talk about logs now
a principle is treat logs as event
streams can you elaborate
yeah the the best way to think about
this is how you would do it otherwise so
it's very common to write your logs to
files that then need to be rotated and
moved off of disk or or whatever it may
be and in that model you have this
operational burden for dealing with
those log files but what the 12 factor
app encourages is this sort of ephemeral
logs flow through standard out and are
captured by some other system that you
don't care about right like the
container is running on a platform and
that platform knows how to capture the
output of your application and send it
somewhere whether it's to a system that
knows how to backup your logs or maybe
it's to a system that knows how to parse
the logs for metrics information or
other key markers that you can use to
monitor the application and so that's
where the treating it as an event stream
really comes in by treating the logs as
events it kind of decouples you from the
various jobs that need to be done with
those events whether it's again
collecting metrics or storing them or
scanning them or searching them is that
also related to telemetry you mentioned
that was something you would add now
yeah I think it's a type of telemetry
and certainly we've in the past at
Heroku encouraged using your logs as a
vehicle for sending metrics to other
systems however it's not the only way to
do that and there are times when you
have a lot of metrics that it puts a
strain on your logging system and so
sending metrics through logs and you
know has problems of its own and
internally at Heroku we've debated
whether this is the right thing to do or
not and I think we've kind of gone back
and forth but there are definitely other
ways to collect metrics there are
systems like Prometheus that are part of
the cloud native ecosystem that I think
provide a better mechanism than actually
putting the metrics into your logs but
certainly your logs are one of the tools
you have for telemetry they're very
useful for security purposes for example
I often recommend logging security
markers for any kind of like privilege
escalation or account login failure or
anything like that it's one of the best
ways to get an early heads-up on a
problem
so the focus for logs is more on the
aggregation is that fair to summarize
that principle yes I think so
the aggregation which leads to searching
storage and other responsibilities
so we've actually covered almost all the
principles except the first and the last
so let's just complete it the first one
says one code based tract in revision
control with multiple deploys so the
code base in revision control certainly
seems like a no-brainer but can you talk
about the mapping between the
recommendation to have a separate
repository for each app yeah there's two
ways you can look at this one is that
you will occasionally see patterns where
developers are sort of forking their
repository for different environments
that they would deploy to so you kind of
have like code specific changes that are
mapped to those environments and that's
something it's it's fairly uncommon but
that's something you want to avoid
I think what this principle is really
kind of driving against is the mono repo
pattern where you have multiple
applications in the same code repository
and then they're deployed to different
places and this is something that again
internally at Heroku there's even though
we wrote the 12 factor app we don't
necessarily agree on this and we do have
some mono repos that we use internally
personally I avoid the mono repo pattern
I find that you end up having commits
that are tied to multiple applications
within that repository which sort of
entangles their history and it makes it
difficult to rollback versions of an app
and without messing something else up so
it's generally something I avoid but I
definitely acknowledge that there are
plenty of use cases where it makes sense
ok let's talk about the last one now
which is related to running admin
processes so this one is confusing why
would you have one often meant processes
the purpose of the a one-off admin
process is isolation and I think this
comes back to thinking about your
processes is being disposable they're
cheap right containers are these
lightweight things that we can spin up
without a lot of resources so let's take
advantage of that because before we had
containers we would SSH or log into a
machine to perform a database job or a
database migration or something like
that and this has definitely happened to
me I've logged into that machine
I've innocently run a database migration
and then accidentally killed the process
that was running in the same machine
that was serving real requests right and
we can avoid that mistake simply by
putting each job whether it's the web
process with a worker process or the
administrative tasks that one-off tasks
for database migrations put it in its
own container
they're cheap they don't require a lot
of resources we have that image that we
created because of how we built our
application and these immutable images
and we might as well take advantage of
that and if you've used technologies
like docker then you're already familiar
with this every time you use docker run
to start a new container that's a
one-off task and that docker run command
really comes from the 12 factor app
because this is the model that Heroku
started with it's Heroku run command
really starting to popularize containers
but now you can have that experience on
your local machine and your communities
cluster or wherever it may be
so what a recommendation around testing
these admin processes these one-off
admin processes is there a process to
test them in stage is a recommendation
around that well I guess by definition
they're kind of these unique little
operations that need to be run I
certainly recommend having tests for the
jobs that you want to run I don't like I
don't think this is this principle is
trying to encourage you to create a
session where you can have an
interactive console and just kind of
poke around at your production data like
be careful there but if you have a rake
task or some other you know script that
is well tested and is meant to be run in
its own isolated process to perform that
administrative task I think that gives
you the appropriate mechanisms to ensure
you're not going to do something
terrible to me it sounds like this
principle is just admitting and being
pragmatic that there will be a need for
these one-off and mend processes and if
there is then follow these principles
yeah I agree
so now that we have covered the 12
factors do you want to take another stab
at why developers should adopt these it
really comes down to scalability and
maintainability by following these
principles
you're just inherently going to create
applications and architectures that are
more resilient to changes in web traffic
or changes and load and that's going to
make it easier for you as a developer as
an operator to maintain that application
when you need to roll out security
patches or do database maintenance if
you're following these principles the
operational burden that you experience
will be reduced and I think the best way
to prove that is to look at the platform
like Heroku we host more than 10 million
applications and we have a couple
hundred engineers running the platform I
don't think that would be possible if it
wasn't for the fact that every single
app on this platform is abiding by these
principles
thanks to on that so my last topic is
really community how can folks learn
more about the 12 factor app well
there's of course the 12 factor dotnet
website which as the original manifesto
but nowadays there's there's many sample
apps and even many of the frameworks
that you're going to use are going to
lend to these principles just naturally
I mentioned before spring boot
just embracing these principles sort of
out of the box but there's also the
underlying technologies because they
favor it so for example docker run I
mentioned and some of the other docker
commands really map well to these
principles so I think the docker
documentation has some examples like a
node.js example which you can put a link
to in the show notes those are probably
the best way to to get started actually
see what a12 factor app looks like and I
think you'll find that it looks like
most other apps it's really about how
you operate on it and what development
process is you use to to change it and
to deploy it will definitely put a link
to the app that you point to in the show
notes as well as a link to your blog is
there a way for people to contribute if
somebody wants to do so further to the
effort of popularizing these factors for
for anyone that's passionate about
encouraging this pattern certainly link
back to the 12 factor dotnet website I
think it's a great topic for someone who
is either a first times conference
speaker who wants to give a conference
talk because there's there are a lot of
materials out there to learn from and I
feel like it's the kind of topic that a
lot of both new developers and old
developers like myself need to hear
because these principles they seem to be
timeless in a way like granted 8 or 9
years is not an eternity but in tech
that can be a pretty long time so I
think it's a great topic for people to
take a stab at practicing their blogging
skills or conference speaking skills and
share the share the ideas of the 12
factor app
how can people get in touch with you so
I go by code finger on most social media
and Internet places except github where
I am Jay Kutner happy to field questions
there or any other place you can find me
whether it's IRC or slack I will put up
with that in the show notes Joe thank
you very much for coming on the show and
talking about the 12 factors thank you
for having me this is conscience shrinky
for software engineering radio
developers take your marks it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris it's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible it's time to
use any data from any source it's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces so what are
you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner system's iris Data Platform the
fastest way to build applications ready
set code start coding for free visit
inner systems.com slash try to try iris
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening